Lucy Ann Lewis Horton Papers
Lucy Ann Lewis Horton Papers
1836-1924
Horton, Lucy Ann Lewis, 1812-1901.
1.0 linear feet
Papers of Lucy Ann Lewis and her husband David M. Horton. Collection contains genealogical material of the Lewis family of Oneida County, New York, account books, diaries, and photographs. Of special interest is a diary kept by Mrs. Horton, 1877-1878, with daily summaries of commodity prices, weather, and her daily workload, as well as reference to her husband's business, and news items.
148788
Biographical History
Lucy Ann Lewis (1812-1901) was a housewife in 19th century Whitestown, New York.
Lucy was born in Whitestown, Oneida County, New York on December 13, 1812. Her parents were William R. and Charlotte Lewis. She married David Millard Horton in Sennett on January 10, 1842, the marriage being performed by the Rev. G.W.Montgomery. David Horton was born on June 13, 1819 at the Horton homestead in Throop. He inherited a thriving and prosperous farm from his family, and also ran a coal and phosphate business. He was a member of the Democratic party. He was active in community affairs.
The Hortons had four children, Charlotte, Josephine, William L. and Hiram F. Charlotte married Leander J. Olmstead of Des Moines, Iowa, and had two children, Millard A. and Clarence. Josephine married J. M. Treat, and had two children Edna and Lulu. Hiram married Lucy M. Skeel.
Lucy Ann Lewis Horton kept a diary for two years, in 1877 and 1878, which gives insight into her daily life. It also gives a picture of the great physical demands on women of that era and the enormous work-loads they managed each day. On March 30, 1877 (age 65) she wrote:
Fri. pleasant baked five loaves of bread fried a half bushel of cakes made 6 pies took up the kitchen carpet - Mrs. Servis came in Lewis went to town sold four doz #12 eggs at 15 per dozen 62 bought 2# raisins for one shilling per pound Mr & Mrs Hopkins came in the eve.
Sun. Jan 14, 1877, tells something of the isolation bad weather could cause:
Sun. snows & blows my head aches they say not a team passed but one.
Mrs. Horton died on October 9, 1901 at the Horton homestead in Throop, Mr. Horton died on April 28, 1907 at the homestead. Both are buried at Pine Hill Cemetery.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lucy Ann Lewis Horton Collection contains genealogical material, two account books (one of Asa Olmstead, the other of William Horton), two diaries (one kept by Lucy Ann Lewis Horton, the other by Lottie H. Horton), photographs and memorabilia.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items are in no particular order.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Women Authors; Horton, David M.; Horton, Lottie.; Horton, Lucy Ann Lewis.; Horton, William L, fl. 1884-1886.; Olmstead, Asa.; Housewives as authors.; Housewives -- United States -- History.; Women -- New York (State) -- Social conditions -- 19th century.; Cayuga County, New York -- Agriculture.; Whitestown (N.Y.) -- History.; Account books.; Diaries.; Genealogies (histories); Photographs.; Housewives.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1970, 1982.
Inventory
- Genealogical materials
  - Lewis family (Box 1)
    The Lewis family - genealogical list (typescript)
    Genealogical chart
    Genealogical list (holograph)
    Genealogical narrative, re Lewis family (typescript)
    Genealogical list (holograph, red ink)
- Account books
  - William L. Horton, 1884-1886; includes business transactions with various persons, comments on the weather, lists names and addresses at the end, an account of his wife's death and funeral (Box 1)
  - Asa Olmstead, 1836-1852; sporadically kept by Mr. Olmstead; lists items sold at auction from his estate on Oct. 21, 1871, with item, price, to whom it was sold; also includes a clipping ("The Year Without A Summer, 1816") (Box 1)
- Diaries
  - Lucy Ann Lewis Horton, 1875 (Box 1)
    This is a day-by-day narrative which gives an account of her life as a mother, wife,and homemaker with interesting insights into the volume, nature, and extent of the work loads carried by women of that era. Reports of the weather and how it affected their daily lives, what certain items cost, the travel options open to people, and the interaction and great dependence of neighbors on each other. Her health, she suffered greatly fro headaches, and that of her friends and relatives was always of concern. Has a page of music theory in front. Also included is a typescript of the diary.
  - Lottie H. Horton, 1865 (Box 1)
    A pocket-sized diary, kept intermittently, difficult to read. The last entry tells of the writer's sadness at not knowing whether a loved one is sick or well, alive or dead, since it has been a year since she last heard from him (perhaps a Civil War separation). The diary does not give a name, nor does it indicate the relationship (brother, father, friend).
  - Author unknown, 1862 (Box 1)
    Author was presumably a young woman, still living at home; the writer talks of parents, household duties, school and friends.
- Photographs
  - Group photo (family?), framed (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    Lucy Horton Payne
    Family group at Uncle Ben's, I886.
    Group picture at the Leonerd Camp, Owasco Lake
    Uncle Ben Lewis's (list of people on back)
    Group picture, four generations - 3 adults, one child
    Group picture - Dr. Peak, Lewises
    Group picture, at cottage on Lake On tario, includes Lewises and Olmsteads
  - Miscellaneous, 1868; 1898,; 1924,; undated (Box 1)
    "Cousin of C.H.O."
    Addie De La Vergne
    Jane Lewis
    Uncle Hiram (Horton)
    Unidentified Horton cousin
    Aunt Charlotte
    Emma Lewis Hoskins
    Asora Lewis Case
    Hiram Frisby
    Minnie Hollenbeck
    Hattie Wadwworth, Oct.20, 1868
    Julia Hollenbeck
    Tintype - Charlotte Frisby
    Laura de Graff Horton
    Adelbert Lewis
    Frank and Emma Lewis Hoskins - snapshot Aug 1924
    Hiram Horton and others in front of Wells Fargo Office
    Horton Reunion - 1898 - includes Lucy Horton
    "Uncle Ben" at his home in Summit, N.J. and others.
- Memorabilia
  - Album of Remembrance (Box 1)
    Provenance Lottie H.Horton, presented by her father, Dec. 25, 1859. Contains "remembrance" poems signed by friends; two paper cut-outs in front of album.
  - Written items (Box 1)
    Pope, Alexander Essay On Man. Ithaca, New York: Andrus, Gauntlett & Co., 1846. Provenance, Miss Charlotte Horton, Pineville.
    Musical Pearls. Syracuse, New York: William F. Hamilton. Cincinnati, Ohio: Jacob Ernst, 1855. John J. Reed, printer, 16 Spruce Street, New York.(song book).Provenance Julia Whaples, includes fragment of "If Animals Behaved As Humans"
  - The 400. Chicago: Persinger & Sullivan, Issue no. 134, Jul 1903; travel brochure (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    Printed card, Millard A. Olmstead
    Reticule, black beaded with black velvet ribbon decoration.Embroidered initials "C.M.L." in white
    Black hemstitched scarf
  - Miscellaneous, combs, buttons (Box 2)